Finding Aid for LaVerne Schmitkons Nethercut papers, 1946-ca. 2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
LaVerne Schmitkons Nethercut papers 1946-ca. 2005 1947-1951
Nethercut, LaVerne Schmitkons, 1929-
2 linear feet and 1 oversize volume
2011105 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by LaVerne Schmitkons Nethercut (donor no. 10532 ) and came to the library in two accessions in 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Vernie (LaVerne) Schmitkons was born in Elyria, Ohio in January 1929. She graduated from the University of Michigan, class of 1951, then taught school for three years. Following her marriage to Gordon Nethercut in 1953, she served as a member of the board of the Northwest Branch of the Detroit YWCA. The Nethercuts later moved to Alpena, Michigan in 1962. From 1964 to 1976, she was part-time communications coordinator for the Alpena Public Schools. In 1977, she founded the Alpena Volunteer Center at Alpena Community College. She served as its director until she retired in 1996.
The LaVerne Schmitkons Nethercut collection consists mainly of materials accumulated while she (Vernie Schmitkons) was a student at the University of Michigan. There is one scrapbook detailing her activities at the University as well as other materials which was intended to be placed in other scrapbook volumes. This material (clippings, memorabilia, receipts, course materials, publications, etc.) documents her involvement in campus activities and organizations. Notable among her activities are files relating to the Student Executive Committee of the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project, course materials from the U-M Department of Physical Education for Women, and a workbook and other materials from the summers she spent as a counselor at the University's National Music Camp at Interlochen. A smaller part of the collection consists of travel brochures for the Alpena area collected for the period of the 1990s up to about 2005.
Subjects:
Nethercut, LaVerne Schmitkons, 1929-; Alpena (Mich.)--Description and travel.; Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project.; National Music Camp.; University of Michigan--Students--1941-1950.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.
- Personal
  - Photos and clippings about her (Box 1)
  - Schmitkons family and Elyria, Ohio miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, largely letters from her parents in Ohio
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948 (Box 1)
    - 1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan Activities and Related Materials, 1947-1951
  - Diaries, appointment calendars, and postcards with grades given for classes (Box 1)
  - Ephemera: programs, name badges, pennants, campaign for office banners (Box 1)
  - Martha Cook Building -- room list, letters, etc. (Box 1)
  - Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project, Student Executive Committee records, 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous: lists, organization materials (Box 1)
  - National Music Camp, 1949-1951
    - Counselor education workbook (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous; include lists, contract, correspondence (Box 1)
  - Notes, tests, essays (mainly English classes) (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Dept. of Physical Education for Women, class notes, syllabi (Box 2)
  - U-M Publications (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1946-1949 (Volume 1)
- Other materials
  - Post-graduation activities as teacher, 1953 and with the public relation committee to the Northwest Board of Management of the Detroit YWCA, 1956-1958 (Box 2)
  - Alpena, Michigan travel and tourist brochures (Box 2)